Alright, we pick up on י"ב עמוד א' Yud Bet Amud Aleph
right near the bottom. אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah, it's about eight lines
from the bottom. אמר רבה בר חיננא סבא משמיה דרב: כל שלא
אמר אמת ויציב שחרית ואמת ואמונה ערבית לא יצא ידי חובתו. Amar
Rabbah bar Chinena Sava mishmei d'Rav: Kol shelo amar Emet Veyatziv shacharit
v'Emet Ve'emunah arvit lo yatza yedei chovato. We've been talking now about
the ברכות brachot that come around the שמע Shema before and after
the שמע. Shema. We discussed the ברכות brachot before of יוצר המאורות
Yotzer HaMeorot and אהבה רבה Ahava Rabbah and talked about how יוצר
המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot was more about the morning and similar מעריב ערבים,
Maariv Aravim, and אהבה רבה Ahava Rabbah and אהבת עולם Ahavat Olam
were about more about the שמע Shema and about תלמוד תורה. Talmud
Torah. We even discussed the possibility for יוצר המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot to
say שמע Shema without יוצר המאורות Yotzer HaMeorot if it's not yet
time fully for the morning, which emphasizes that difference. Now we're moving
into the ברכות brachot at the end, אמת ויציב. Emet Veyatziv. He
says if you don't say אמת ויציב שחרית Emet Veyatziv shacharit and
אמת ואמונה ערבית, Emet Ve'emunah arvit, לא יצא ידי חובתו. lo yatza
yedei chovato. He's not just talking about to say a ברכה bracha
at the end of שמע, Shema, which we know, but he's talking
specifically about the specific language. The same way we had a difference
of מעריב ערבים Maariv Aravim and יוצר המאורות, Yotzer HaMeorot, or which
is obvious, or more subtly, אהבה רבה Ahava Rabbah and אהבת עולם,
Ahavat Olam, here he's saying there's also a difference in the ברכה
bracha afterwards. That it's אמת ויציב Emet Veyatziv in the morning and
אמת ואמונה Emet Ve'emunah in the evening. Why? שנאמר: Shenemar: להגיד בבוקר
חסדך ואמונתך בלילות. Lehagid baboker chasdecha ve'emunatecha baleilot. To
talk about your kindness in the morning and the faith in you
at the night. Presumably again exactly this
difference parallel to the אהבה רבה Ahava Rabbah and אהבת עולם, Ahavat
Olam, that in the morning you really have this appreciation of the
wonderful beneficence and gifts of God and the אהבה רבה, Ahava Rabbah,
life, the sun, the world. In the evening it starts evoking more
sense of fear, the darkness and concern about the night and waking
up the next day, and therefore that's the more אהבת עולם, Ahavat
Olam, the sense of enduring love. Here also the אמת ואמונה, Emet
Ve'emunah, it's the sense of
the faith aspect that's an important part of the night. There's a
nice little parallel in terms of those two.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues. רש"י, Rashi, by the way, if you
look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says two lines before the line get why: וברכת אמת
ויציב כולה על חסד שעשה עם אבותינו שהוציאם ממצרים ובקע להם את
הים
והעבירם. Ubirkhat Emet Veyatziv kulla al chesed she'asa im avoteinu shetziam miMitzrayim
uvaka lahem et hayam vehe'eviram. רש"י Rashi says it's not just the
word יציב, Yatziv, it's the contents of the ברכה. bracha. The אמת
ויציב Emet Veyatziv ברכה bracha in the morning is all about the
נסים, Nissim, all about
the חסד chesed that God has given us. וברכת אמת ואמונה מדבר
בה אף על העתידות. Ubirkhat Emet Ve'emunah medaber ba af al heatidot.
אמת ואמונה Emet Ve'emunah is about hope for the future. מצפים שיקיים
לנו הבטחתו ואמונתו לגואלנו מיד מלכים
וכו'. Metzapim sheykayem lanu havtachato ve'emunato ligoalenu miyad melachim vekhu. I think
again it's not just about praise for the past and hope for
the future, but it is, but it's reflected also by just morning-evening
difference experientially, which is also the אהבה רבה Ahava Rabbah and אהבת
עולם, Ahavat Olam, אהבה רבה Ahava Rabbah and אהבת עולם. Ahavat Olam.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues: ואמר רבה בר
חיננא סבא משמיה דרב, V'amar Rabbah bar Chinena Sava mishmei d'Rav, המתפלל
כשהוא כורע כורע בברוך. Hamitpallel keshu koreia koreia beBaruch. If somebody מתפלל
mitpallel when they are bending down, then they should bend down at
ברוך. Baruch. וכשהוא זוקף זוקף בשם. Ukeshu zokef zokef beShem. I put
the comma in the wrong place. המתפלל, Hamitpallel, one who davens, כשהוא
כורע כורע בברוך. keshu koreia koreia beBaruch. When you do the bowing,
you bow at ברוך. Baruch. וכשהוא זוקף Ukeshu zokef and when you
do the standing up, זוקף בשם, zokef beShem, you do it when
you say שם ה'. Shem Hashem. It's ברוך אתה, Baruch Atah, you
bend your knees at the ברוך Baruch and then you're bowed down
at the אתה, Atah, and then when you say God's name, you're
bowing up as it were, you're becoming erect at the name of
God.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, מאי טעמא דרב? mai ta'ama d'Rav? דכתיב: Dikhitiv:
ה' זוקף כפופים. Hashem zokef kefufim. God causes those that are bent
to be standing up, to be upright. Therefore the name of God
makes us from that bent state to the upright state. The גמרא
Gemara says: מיתיבי Meitvei ask you on this: מפני שמי נחת. Mipnei
shemi nichat. Because of my name he is
humbled. You see God's name causes that sense of being lowly, of
humility, and not of standing up. The גמרא Gemara says: מי כתיב
בשמי, Mi ktiv bishmi,
with the articulation of my name?
Excuse me, of my name. מפני שמי כתיב, Mipnei shemi ktiv,
because of my name. My name causes that sense of humility but
in the utterance of God's name, that actually causes us to rise.
Again this is this dialectic and tension that I think we've been
seeing before, that praying to God on the one hand has to
imbue us with a tremendous sense of awe and humility and our
smallness, and at the other hand, we're reaching reaching out to God,
which is that sense of connection. So before we had, you stand
in a low place, but you stand with your feet combined like
an angel. So both that sense of where we're striving for connection
and that sense of our humility. So here too, you have the
bowing down, that sense that we're nothing, we're on the ground, in
the presence of God, but then also the saying of God's name,
the reaching out to connect is also what rises us up. So
I think that's a beautiful play in terms of the sort of
competing themes that are going on here. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה שמואל לחייא בר רב. Amar lei Shmuel leChiya bar Rav.
So שמואל Shmuel said to חייא בר רב, Chiya bar Rav, בר
אוריין, Bar Orayan,
which could mean son of a lion or could mean a תלמיד
חכם, Talmid Chacham, like אורייתא, Orayta, תורה. Torah. תא אימא לך מלתא
מעליא דאמר אבוך. Ta ima lach milta ma'alyata d'amar avuch. Go tell
us something nice that your father said. תא אימא לך Ta ima
lach
let me tell you. Boy, okay. Let me tell you something beautiful
that your father said. הכי אמר אבוך Hachi amar avuch here's what
your father said. כשהוא כורע כורע בברוך וכשהוא זוקף זוקף בשם. Keshehu
kore'a, kore'a be'Baruch, u'keshehu zokef, zokef be'Shem. Exactly what we said before.
So here he is reporting it to שמואל Shmuel is reporting it
to חייא בר רב Chiya bar Rav in the name of his
father, like we saw before, that this was taught in the name
of רב. Rav. Turning to page י"ב עמוד ב', yod bet amud
bet, רב ששת כי כרע כרע כחיזרא. Rav Sheshet ki kara, kara
k'chizra.
When רב ששת Rav Sheshet bowed down, he would bow down like
a rod. Like why he says, like if you threw a rod
to the ground, it would be like falling down immediately,
in one shot,
without hesitation. וכי זקיף זקיף כחיויא, u'ki zakif, zakif k'chivra, and when
he would rise up,
he would rise up like a snake, the way a snake sort
of slowly rises, like the snake charmer's or whatever, as they rise
off the ground from their head, very slow and gradual. So again,
sort of emphasizing,
רש"י Rashi says that the bowing down should not look like a
משא, massa, like you're quick to get up. So emphasizing the immediate
sense of your sense of awe in coming before God and the
reaction is immediate and then sort of gaining the strength to rise
up and to, which is a slow process. So again, playing with
that tension but giving the emphasis towards that sense of awe that
has to sort of the weight has to be put on that.
ואמר רבה בר חיננא סבא משמיה דרב. V'amar Rabba bar Chinena Sava
mishmei de'Rav. And now another teaching from the same tradition, רבה בר
חיננא Rabba bar Chinena in the name of רב. Rav. כל השנה
כולה. Kol hashanah kullah. And now this is not related, it's related
to דאבנינג davening but not the immediate issues we're talking about, but
it is the same
אמורא. amora. כל השנה כולה אדם מתפלל האל הקדוש. Kol hashanah kullah,
adam mitpallel Ha'El HaKadosh. The whole year when you say the first,
the third ברכה bracha of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei you say האל
הקדוש Ha'El HaKadosh and you say מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט Melech Ohev
Tzedakah u'Mishpat when you say the ברכה bracha of משפט Mishpat in
the middle, it's מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט. Melech Ohev Tzedakah u'Mishpat. That's
our נוסח nusach of course, חוץ מעשרת ימים שבין ראש השנה ויום
הכיפורים, chutz m'aseret yamim shebein Rosh Hashanah v'Yom Kippur, except for the
עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. This is technically inaccurate; they're not
ten days between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
there's only seven days, but it means the ten days encompassing ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the עשרת ימי תשובה.
Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. There we say, what do you say there? שמתפלל
המלך הקדוש והמלך המשפט. She'mitpallel HaMelech HaKadosh v'HaMelech HaMishpat. There the sense
of God's מלכות malchut dominates and therefore you say not האל הקדוש
Ha'El HaKadosh but המלך הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh and you don't say מלך
אוהב צדקה ומשפט Melech Ohev Tzedakah u'Mishpat
but God embodies משפט. mishpat. There the shift is not מלך, Melech,
מלך Melech was always part of that ברכה, bracha, but it's המלך
המשפט HaMelech HaMishpat that that is so much the emphasis of משפט
mishpat as the identity of God at that time. So both מלך
Melech is being emphasized and משפט. mishpat. By the way, I should
mention that המלך הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh is really what we say on
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That there doesn't
seem to have been a debate that that's the נוסח nusach of
the ברכה bracha on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, המלך הקדוש. HaMelech HaKadosh. But the question is, do you extend
that ברכה bracha into the עשרת ימי תשובה Aseret Yemei Teshuvah and
then you also pattern similarly after it
המלך המשפט. HaMelech HaMishpat. So he said yes, and that's what you
have even in the עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. רבי אליעזר
אמר אפילו אמר האל הקדוש יצא. Rabbi Eliezer amar afilu amar Ha'El
HaKadosh yatza. Maybe ideally you should do that, but בדיעבד bedieved you're
יוצא yotzei even if you say האל הקדוש. Ha'El HaKadosh. שנאמר ויגבה
ה' צבאות במשפט והאל הקדוש נקדש בצדקה. Shene'emar Vayigbah Hashem Tzeva'ot bamishpat
v'ha'El hakadosh nikdash bitzedakah. So the glory of God is lifted up
in judgment and the holy God is sanctified in righteousness. אימתי ויגבה
ה' צבאות במשפט. Eimatai Vayigbah Hashem Tzeva'ot bamishpat. When is God sort
of the focus on justice? אלו עשרת ימים שבין ראש השנה ליום
הכיפורים Elu aseret yamim she'beRosh Hashanah l'Yom Kippur and this is the
עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. And even during that time when
the emphasis is God as judge, וקאמר האל הקדוש. v'ka'amar Ha'El HaKadosh.
And nevertheless the end of the פסוק pasuk is האל הקדוש. Ha'El
HaKadosh. So you see האל הקדוש Ha'El HaKadosh is acceptable during that
time and presumably if האל הקדוש Ha'El HaKadosh is acceptable מלך אוהב
צדקה ומשפט Melech Ohev Tzedakah u'Mishpat is also acceptable. מאי הוי עלה,
Mai havya alah, what was the upshot of this? אמר רב יוסף
האל הקדוש ומלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט. Amar Rav Yosef Ha'El HaKadosh u'Melech
Ohev Tzedakah u'Mishpat. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says you keep the normal
נוסח nusach presumably not even בדיעבד bedieved even לכתחילה, lechatchila, if you
say המלך הקדוש, ha-Melech ha-Kadosh, you say it on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, not on עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret
Yemei Teshuva. רבה אמר, Rabba amar, המלך הקדוש ha-Melech ha-Kadosh והמלך המשפט.
ve-ha-Melech ha-Mishpat. No, you change the גרסא girsa to what we to
המלך הקדוש ha-Melech ha-Kadosh והמלך המשפט ve-ha-Melech ha-Mishpat והלכתא כרבה ve-hilchata ke-Rabba
and we rule like רבה Rabba as we know that is our
פסק. psak. Interestingly, take a quick look at תוספות, Tosafot, והלכתא כוותיה
דרבה. ve-hilchata kavatei de-Rabba. תוספות Tosafot says וצריך לחתום המלך הקדוש המלך
המשפט ואם לא אמר מחזירין אותו, ve-tzarich lach-tom ha-Melech ha-Kadosh ha-Melech ha-Mishpat
ve-im lo amar machzirin oto, so it's merely, if you made a
mistake, you have to go back. שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei doesn't count.
And then it says, וכן זכרנו לחיים מי כמוך וכתוב לחיים ובספר
חיים מחזירין אותו אם לא אמר. ve-chein Zachreinu le-Chaim Mi Chamocha u-Ktov
le-Chaim u-ve-Sefer Chaim machzirin oto im lo amar. So all these additions,
זכרנו, Zachreinu, מי כמוך, Mi Chamocha, all these things which as we
know were added by the גאונים, Geonim, תוספות Tosafot first says once
they're added they become part of the נוסח nusach and if you
don't say it you have to go back. Then in the end
תוספות Tosafot says, if you're looking near the bottom by the asterisk,
ורבינו תם ve-Rabbeinu Tam or anyway whoever it is, רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu
Chananel, anyway כתב דאין מחזירין אותם מכל אותן דברים דלא פסק בש"ס
בפירוש. katav de-ein machzirin otam mi-kol otan devarim de-lo pasak ba-Shas be-feirush.
Maybe right? These things were added later by the גאונים Geonim and
therefore if you don't say them you don't go back and that
is how we פסקן. pasken. You go back for המלך הקדוש ha-Melech
ha-Kadosh and המלך המשפט ha-Melech ha-Mishpat but not for the זכרנו'ס Zachreinu's
and וכתבנו'ס u-Ktovenu's and so on which were added later.
Okay, so now we have three teachings of this רבה בר חיננא
Rabba bar Chinana in the name of
רב. Rav. One which started us, which was אמת ויציב ואמת ואמונה,
Emet ve-Yatziv ve-Emet ve-Emunah, the ברכה bracha after שמע, Shema, and now
two הלכות halachot about שמונה עשרה: Shemoneh Esrei: bowing down and
מלך צדקה המלך המשפט. Melech tzedakah ha-Melech ha-Mishpat. ואמר רבה בר חיננא
סבא משמיה דרב, Ve-amar Rabba bar Chinana Sava mishmeih de-Rav, and now
again רבה בר חיננא Rabba bar Chinana in the name of רב,
Rav, yet another thing: כל שאפשר לו לבקש רחמים על חבירו ואינו
מבקש נקרא חוטא. Kol she-efshar lo levakesh rachamim al chaveiro ve-eino mevakesh
nikra chotei. Again in the realm of דאווענינג, davening, but not about
the נוסח, nusach, but about an attitude towards דאווענינג. davening. If you
can pray for your friend, you know that somebody you know needs
your prayers, needs רחמים, rachamim, needs some type of divine aid and
you don't pray for that person, you're a sinner. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, as
the פסוק pasuk says, גם אנכי חלילה לי מחטא לה' מחדול להתפלל
בעדכם. Gam anochi chalila li me-chato la-Hashem me-chadol le-hitpaleil ba'adchem. As for
me, God forbid for me
to sin against God
that I should hold back from praying for your sake. So you
see that it would be a sin not to pray for somebody's
sake. And it seems like the point here is, you know, it's
interesting, you know, because I would say a couple of things. Number
one is that, you know, in general, people do statutory prayer, you
know, the things that are obligated. That doesn't really speak so much
towards, you know, a sense of real faith in how God operates
in the world. I mean, it is the content of it, but
you do it because you have to. When you're responding to a
situation
and you pray because something's actually happening, that shows like a real,
I think, a deeper belief in the fact that, you know, the
role that God can play in the world. If that were just
the only point, then it wouldn't just be about חבירו, chaveiro, it
would be even about yourself. You know, that if you're not praying
in response to something happening to you, that might show like a
certain lack of faith. The חבירו chaveiro aspect obviously is adding another
component. It's adding the basic sense about caring about your friend. You
know, so if you, A, if you have this faith that prayer
helps and God is involved in the world, and B, if your
friend needs it and you're not doing it, then you're a sinner
because you are, you know, abandoning your friend in this way. So
that really gives this whole power to, you know, the efficacy of
prayer and how it's something we do not just because we have
to, but we do it, it's a way of helping people and
that sense of responsibility towards that. And then the גמרא Gemara continues
and says, אמר רבא אם תלמיד חכם הוא צריך שיחלה עצמו עליו.
Amar Rava im talmid chacham hu tzarich she-ye-chaleh atzmo alav. And if
the person who needs your prayers is a
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, it's not just enough to pray, you have
to even like make yourself sick over the person, presumably because you're
so much, you know, involved in your prayer. You really have to
go the extra mile. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why, what's the reason?
אילימא משום דכתיב, Ilima mishum de-chtiv, what's the reason? If I say
because the פסוק pasuk says, ואין חולה מכם עלי וגולה את אזני.
ve-ein choleh mikem alay ve-goleh et ozni. Nobody, this was שאול Shaul
complaining about being informed about דוד. David. Nobody cares about me, is
concerned about me, or is revealing to my ear what's going on.
But the גמרא's Gemara's reading it literally, חולה, choleh, nobody's getting, you're
not getting, making yourself sick over me. You know, so it's really
like the, you
know, it's like a classic Jewish mother. You know, you know you
love somebody when you get sick over them. So anyway, so דילמא
מלך שאני, dilma melech shani, maybe that's just for the king you
should make yourself sick, not for just a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מהכא, ella me-hacha, from here: ואני
בחלותם לבושי, Va-ani be-chalotam levushi, and I in their illness, you know,
I dressed in the sackcloth and so on. So this is דוד
David talking about how he, you know, afflicted himself. Now again, the
simple sense of the פסוק pasuk is that he afflicted himself when
others became ill. But we're reading it presumably that he made himself...
self ill for their sake. So that's taking it even beyond just
obviously the issue of prayer. ואמר רבי חנינא בר סבא משמיה דרב,
Ve'amar Rabbi Chinana bar Sabba mishmei deRav, again, רבי חנינא בר סבא
Rabbi Chinana bar Sabba in the name of רב, Rav, כל העושה
דבר עבירה ומתבייש בו. kol ha'oseh devar aveirah umitbayesh bo. Now we're
shifting from prayer to different areas, although of course there is a
very common theme here. He's not talking to us about הלכות halachot
about, you know, גרמי. garmi. I mean, it's very much about these
sort of religious, ethical types of teachings. That anybody who does a
sin and is embarrassed by it, is sort of shamed by what
he has done, מוחלין לו כל עונותיו, mochalin lo kol avonotav, all
of his sins are forgiven. This connects, I probably, to the theme
we talked earlier, you know, where the גמרא Gemara says like, if
you can, if you internalize a message, it's better than being like,
you know, getting a hundred lashes. That when if you actually feel
the shame and feel the embarrassment and you internalize that, that can
have a profound transformation of your personality and of your future actions.
And that's what I think the idea of מוחלין לו כל עונותיו—it's
mochalin lo kol avonotav not just like, oh you're suffering and that
causes atonement, but it's actually that the feeling of the shame hopefully
can really lead to a transformative experience. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says,
למען תזכרי ובושת ולא
יהיה לך עוד פתחון פה מפני כלימתך בכפרי לך לכל אשר עשית
נאם ה׳ אלקים. Lema'an tizkeri uvoshatch velo yihyeh lach od pitchon peh
mipnei kelimatech bechappri lach lechol asher asit ne'um Hashem Elokim. In order
that you should remember and be embarrassed, and you will no longer
have any response because of your shame, when I atone for you
for all that you have done, says God, נאם ה׳ אלקים. ne'um
Hashem Elokim. So there you see, the way it's reading it is
because you have the shame and embarrassment, therefore I will atone for
you. So the גמרא Gemara says, דילמא ציבור שאני? Dilma tzibbur shani?
Maybe that was when the entire ציבור, tzibbur, all of כל ישראל,
Klall Yisrael, was shamed, which is the sort of story there that
we'll be shown up for our sins. Maybe that's different, that's of
a different character. אלא מהכא, Ella meihacha, how do you know about
an individual? From the following פסוק. pasuk. ויאמר שמואל אל שאול, Vayomer
Shmuel el Shaul, שמואל Shmuel said to שאול Shaul when שאול Shaul
raised up שמואל Shmuel from the dead, or his spirit, למה הרגזתני
להעלות אותי, Lamah hirgaztani leha'alot oti, why did you disturb me to
raise me up? ויאמר שאול, Vayomer Shaul, and שאול Shaul said, צר
לי מאד ופלשתים נלחמים בי ואלקים סר מעלי ולא ענני עוד גם
ביד הנביאים גם בחלומות ואקראה לך להודיעני מה אעשה. Tzar li me'od
uPlishtim nilchamim bi v'Elokim sar me'alai velo anani od gam beyad hanevi'im
gam bachalomot va'ekre'ah lecha lehodi'eni mah e'eseh. I'm very anguished, afflicted, and
the Philistines are fighting against
me, and God has departed from me, and He hasn't answered me
through prophets, not through
dreams. Therefore I had to raise your spirit up so you could
tell me how I should act. So that's what he said. And
now the גמרא Gemara comments on this: ואילו אורים ותומים לא קאמר,
V'illu Urim v'Tummim lo ka'amar, but he didn't say, I tried the
אורים ותומים Urim v'Tummim and I didn't get an answer from the
אורים ותומים. Urim v'Tummim. Why didn't he say that? משום דקטליה לנוב
עיר הכהנים, Mishum dekatlei leNov ir hakohanim, because there was nobody to
ask the אורים ותומים Urim v'Tummim or because he had wiped out
the entire city of כהנים. kohanim. So there was, you know, so
it was very hard to go ask the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
the אורים ותומים Urim v'Tummim after having wiped out that entire city.
So the גמרא Gemara understands that because he didn't mention it, that
shows that he was embarrassed about that and embarrassed about what he
had done to wipe out the entire city. And therefore he was
avoiding saying it. Now, as far as you and me are concerned,
you know, not talking about something that you did wrong doesn't necessarily
reflect the greatest degree of shame or embarrassment. But nevertheless, for the
גמרא, Gemara, that's significant enough to say that look, he actually had
a sense of the wrongness of his deed. And therefore, ומנא דאחלו
ליה מן שמיא, Umena de'achlu lei min shamaya,
so how do we prove our point that as a result of
that he was forgiven? שנאמר, Shene'emar, because the פסוק pasuk says, ומחר
אתה ובניך עמי. Umachar atah uvannecha immi. That שמואל Shmuel said to
שאול, Shaul,
tomorrow you and your children will be with me, because they were
going to die in that war. So what does that prove? It
just means they'll die. No. ואמר
רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, עמי במחיצתי. immi bimchitzati. You will be
in my מחיצה, mechitzah, in my special region in the world to
come. So therefore, you will have merit to the world to come,
and why will that be? Because since you were embarrassed and you
didn't mention this thing that you had done wrong, you, all of
your sins will be forgiven. So it's a pretty low level of
embarrassment, I would say, that's being asked of us. ורבנן אמרי מהכא,
Verabbanan amri meihacha, and the Rabbis say from the following פסוק: pasuk:
והוקענום לה׳ בגבעת שאול בחיר ה׳. Vehoka'anum l'Hashem beGivat Shaul bechir Hashem.
This is when, you know, דוד David asked the גבעונים Givonim who's,
you know, about how to atone for the sins of שאול Shaul
and so on, and they said, take the sons of שאול Shaul
and sort of and put, you know, and basically spear them and
rise them up on, you know, in front of God, in the
sun in the presence of God. So what does that prove? Because
it says בחיר ה׳. bechir Hashem. Here the גבעונים Givonim are talking
about the way שאול Shaul had sinned against them and
they're calling him the chosen of God. So the גמרא Gemara says,
it's not the גבעונים Givonim who are saying it; it's the narrator
who's saying בחיר ה׳. bechir Hashem. יצתה בת קול ואמרה. Yatzta bat
kol ve'amra.
the גבעונים Givonim said, you know, sort of do this to the
sons of שאול Shaul and a heavenly voice said, oh, שאול, Shaul,
he's בחיר השם. bechir Hashem. So why is שאול Shaul בחיר? bechir?
Must be because he was embarrassed and he didn't mention the story
of נוב עיר כהנים. Nov Ir Kohanim. Okay, so that was pretty
interesting, I mean, you know, from the degree of shame you would
think would be required to make such a statement to what we
see actually occurred by שאול. Shaul. Now the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבי אבא בן זוטרא אמר רבי יהודה בר זבידא. Amar Rabbi Abba
ben Zutra amar Rabbi Yehuda bar Zvida. Now that's the end of
our אגדתא, Agadata, our digression, or not אגדתא, Agadata, but whatever, our
digression, went from a statement about the nature of אמת ואמונה Emet
Ve'emuna and אמת ויציב. Emet Ve'yatziv. And now we go back to
talking about the liturgy around קריאת שמע. Kriyas Shema. So let's take
a look.
Is there a question? No.
If somebody could put it on mute please unless you have a
question. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אמר רבי אבא בר זוטרתי אמר רבי יהודה בר זבידא, Amar
Rabbi Abba bar Zutrati amar Rabbi Yehuda bar Zvida, בקשו לקבוע פרשת
בלק בקריאת שמע. bikshu likboa Parshas Balak biKriyas Shema. They wanted part
of קריאת שמע Kriyas Shema to include the פרשה parsha of בלק.
Balak. That's pretty fascinating. Which aspect of it? There's a lot of
that פרשה. parsha. Anyway, ומפני מה לא קבעוה? u'mipnei mah lo keva'uha?
Why didn't they do it? משום טורח ציבור. mishum torach tzibur. Because
maybe they wanted to include all of the beautiful prophecies. It's not
clear how much of that they wanted to include, but anyway it
would have been super long. So therefore they didn't include it. So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why did they want
to include it? What was powerful about it?
אילימא משום דכתיב בה
ilima
mishum
dechtiv ba אל מוציאם ממצרים. El motzi'am miMitzrayim.
Maybe it's because it says, you know, the God brought them out
of Egypt. So maybe it was a substitute for the פרשת ציצית,
Parshas Tzitzis, which is about יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So that's usually
the major function of the פרשת ציצית Parshas Tzitzis is יציאת מצרים.
Yetzias Mitzrayim. We do two מצוות mitzvos in קריאת שמע. Kriyas Shema.
We do the מצווה mitzvah of קריאת שמע Kriyas Shema and the
third פרשה parsha is a separate מצווה mitzvah of remembering יציאת מצרים.
Yetzias Mitzrayim. So it didn't have to be the ציצית. Tzitzis.
Maybe the remembering of יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim could have been done
by reading the פרשה parsha of בלק Balak and reading the פסוק
pasuk of אל מוציאם ממצרים. El motzi'am miMitzrayim.
So that says they actually wanted to do that and they would
have done it had it not been that long. So then the
גמרא Gemara continues and says the following. It says אלא, ela, wait
a minute, לימא פרשת ריבית ופרשת
משקלות. leima Parshas Ribis u'Parshas Mishkolos. So it talks about God taking
us out of Egypt in a lot of places. It says it
about the prohibition of ריבית Ribis or about just weights, you know,
it says about God having taken us out of Egypt. דכתיב בהן
יציאת מצרים. dechtiv bahen Yetzias Mitzrayim. So that it couldn't have been
that alone. אלא אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין, ela amar Rabbi Yosi
bar Avin, משום דכתיב בה האי קרא. mishum dechtiv ba hai kra.
No, it's more than just יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. There's other aspects
that are important. It says כרע שכב כארי וכלביא מי יקימנו, kara
shachav ka'ari u'chelavia mi yekimenu, that, you know, we בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael crouched down like a lion and like a, again, like a
lion, like a whelp, who will rise us up? So רש"י Rashi
says that exactly parallels קריאת שמע, Kriyas Shema, lying down and rising
up. So if we're looking for a way to include יציאת מצרים
Yetzias Mitzrayim and קריאת שמע, Kriyas Shema, why not do it through
פרשת בלק Parshas Balak that echoes the theme of קריאת שמע? Kriyas
Shema? So the גמרא Gemara says ולימא האי פסוקא ותו לא? v'leima
hai pasuka v'su lo? So fine, so don't say the whole thing,
say that פסוק pasuk and say אל מוציאם ממצרים, El motzi'am miMitzrayim,
and then we'll be done. So you don't need טורח ציבור. torach
tzibur. You'll just do the key components. So the גמרא Gemara says
גמירי, gmiri, no, we have a
tradition, כל פרשה דפסקה משה רבינו פסקינן. kol parsha d'paska Moshe Rabbeinu
paskinan. Any פרשה parsha that משה Moshe divided, we can divide. דלא
פסקה משה רבינו לא פסקינן. d'la paska Moshe Rabbeinu la paskinan. If
משה Moshe didn't divide it, we can't divide it. So we can't
just do selections from בלק. Balak. It's either all of it or
none of it. Now I should say by the way that sometimes
the line is כל פסוק דלא פסקה משה לא פסקינן, kol pasuk
d'la paska Moshe la paskinan, and here it's כל פרשה דלא פסקה
משה, kol parsha d'la paska Moshe, and the difference seems to be
that the כל פסוק, kol pasuk, we don't divide a פסוק, pasuk,
even when we're talking you should say a whole פסוק. pasuk. Which
is by the way when the גמרא Gemara quotes a part of
a פסוק, pasuk, it always says וגומר v'gomer as opposed to וכולי.
v'chulu. I don't know if people are aware of the difference. Both
וכולי v'chulu and וגומר v'gomer mean etcetera, dot dot dot. But וכולי
v'chulu is used when it's not quoting a פסוק. pasuk. וגומר v'gomer
is used when it's quoting a פסוק, pasuk, because the idea when
you quote a פסוק pasuk is you have to end it, you
have to complete it, וגומר. v'gomer. So say the whole פסוק. pasuk.
Anyway, there the issue is more about, is more about, you know,
that even as an individual, you know, when you're talking you're not
supposed to say half of a פסוק. pasuk. Although there is interesting
תשובה teshuva of רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef where he actually
says there's no problem doing it and especially like if you're learning
גמרא Gemara and so on you don't have to end the פסוק.
pasuk. But anyway, here when we don't divide a פרשה, parsha, that's
more in terms of using it as a part of the liturgy.
That you know you can obviously quote a פסוק pasuk without quoting
the whole פרשה, parsha, but to make something part of the liturgy,
we're not going to do a half of a פרשה. parsha. So
that's why we do not do בלק. Balak. So now the גמרא
Gemara continues, okay, so פרשת ציצית מפני מה קבעוה? Parshas Tzitzis mipnei
mah keva'uha? Is there a question? No. I yes, we say רצה
והחליצנו rtzeh v'hachlitzenu and that's just one verse in.
I'm sorry? When we say מה טובו Mah Tovu every day and
that's one... Yeah, that's an interesting point.
Yeah, but you know מה טובו Mah Tovu is,
again, that's
not like of the official rabbinic liturgy. You know, there's no הלכה,
halacha, you know,
they didn't require us, there's no הלכה halacha about it. It's מנהג
minhag really, saying מה טובו. Mah Tovu. But you're right, you know,
it does sort of draw the line. What is considered, I mean
we say a lot of פסוקים psukim and you know, there's one
part by the way in the פסוקי דזמרא Psukei D’zimra which is
just a collection of פסוקים psukim from all over the place, you
know, the part that we say in the middle before between ברוך
שאמר Baruch She’amar and אשרי. Ashrei. So you're right, it does raise
a question like what's considered like official liturgy that has this requirement
and what's not. So, you know, here the real part חז"ל Chazal
emphasize as the official liturgy was שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, שמע, Shema,
וברכות קריאת שמע. uvirkhot kriyat Shema. You know, פסוקי דזמרא, Psukei D’zimra,
even פסוקי דזמרא Psukei D’zimra is much more fluid and whatever. So
those are the עיקר ikar sort of liturgy here of חז"ל, Chazal,
but it's a good question. I mean, we're not really consistent about
these rules, I have to tell you about the whole פרשיות parshas
and the whole פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so now let's see how the
גמרא Gemara continues. It says, so okay, so we know we want
to say, do this other מצוה mitzva of יציאת מצרים. Yetziat Mitzrayim.
And but why pick ציצית? tzitzit? You could have picked a lot
of things. So now we're going to talk about that. So ופרשת
ציצית מפני מה קבעוה? uvarshat tzitzit mifnei mah k’vauha? So why did
they pick ציצית? tzitzit? אמר רב יהודה בר חביבא מפני שיש בה
חמשה דברים, Amar Rav Yehuda bar Chaviva mifnei sheyesh bah chamisha devarim,
because it has not just יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim, it has five
things. What does it have? מצות ציצית, mitzvot tzitzit, which is בעצם
be’etzem the מצוה; mitzva; יציאת מצרים; Yetziat Mitzrayim; עול מצוות, Ol Mitzvot,
it also has the sense of the yoke of מצוות, mitzvot, ועשיתם
את כל מצוותי, va’asitem et kol mitzvotai, which certainly parallels the theme
of the earlier פרשיות parshas of שמע, Shema, of doing the מצוות;
mitzvot; דעת מינים, Da’at Minim, knowledge of heresy. What does that mean?
והרהור עבירה, vehirhur aveira, sinful thoughts, these are bad things, not good
things; והרהור עבודה זרה vehirhur avoda zara and thoughts of idolatry. What
the heck does that mean? So let's take a look. בשלמא הני
תלתא מפרשן, Bishlama hani tlata meparshin, the first three we get: עול
מצוות דכתיב וראיתם אותו וזכרתם את כל מצוות ה', Ol Mitzvot d’chtiv
ur’item oto uzchartem et kol mitzvot Hashem, the עול מצוות Ol Mitzvot
because it says, you know, you see them and remember the מצוות;
mitzvot; ציצית דכתיב עשו לכם ציצית, tzitzit d’chtiv asu lachem tzitzit, okay,
ציצית tzitzit is obvious; ויציאת מצרים דכתיב אשר הוצאתי אתכם. viyetziat Mitzrayim
d’chtiv asher hotzeiti etchem. The first three we get, okay, and of
course as we said, the benefit of the עול מצוות Ol Mitzvot
besides that it's intrinsically benefit is it ties into the theme of
שמע. Shema. But אלא דעת מינים הרהור עבירה והרהור עבודה זרה מנלן,
ela Da’at Minim hirhur aveira vehirhur avoda zara minalan, but how about
these last things? So the גמרא Gemara says there's a problem, if
you count there's six, not five, so some on the side switch
the גירסא girsa to six. Anyway, where do you get them? דתניא,
D’tanya, אחרי לבבכם, acharei levavchem, that you look at the ציצית tzitzit
and you do not stray after your hearts, זו מינות, zu minus,
that's heresy. Heart sometimes for us is about emotion, but heart also
can refer to, you know, intellect and thought, at least, you know,
in the sort of at the in חז"ל Chazal and in their
metaphor. So therefore, don't stray after your hearts means don't be misled
by, you know, heretical thoughts, don't let your intellect lead you lead
you astray from the true faith. And by looking at the ציצית
tzitzit you'll keep on the straight and narrow. וכן הוא אומר אמר
נבל בלבו אין אלהים, v’khen hu omer amar naval belibo ein Elohim,
the degenerate one says in his heart there is no God. So
that's a heretical thought and that's בלבו, belibo, in your heart. So
the ציצית tzitzit keep you keep you focused, you know, remembering what
you're supposed to be thinking and believing. ואחרי עיניכם, v’acharei eineichem, don't
stray after your eyes, זו הרהור עבירה, zu hirhur aveira, that is
about sexual sin. שנאמר ויאמר שמשון לאביו אותה קח לי כי היא
ישרה בעיני. Shene’emar vayomer Shimshon le’aviv otah kach li ki hi yashra
be’einai. Shimshon says to his father, I want that woman that I
found amongst the פלשתים, Plishtim, she is fit in my eyes. And
there it's בעיני, be’einai, found, you know, so seeing a woman, a
man seeing a woman and desiring her is very much the emphasis
about the visual. So after your eyes is the sense of of
being led away about led after sexual sin. אשר אתם זונים, Asher
atem zonim, that you fornicate, which sounds to be sexual sins, זה
הרהור עבודה זרה. ze hirhur avoda zara. No, that is actually talking
about thinking about idolatry. וכן הוא אומר ויזנו אחרי הבעלים, v’khen hu
omer vayiznu acharei habalim, they fornicated after the בעלים, Ba’alim, after the
false god, because very often the metaphor is בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
and God is like a marriage, and when we worship false gods,
we are committing adultery, we are fornicating and so on. So that
is that it has all those three elements. Now, of course, the
point to point out here is not just that these are intrinsically
important and why not, it's a great packed פרשה parsha and it
has יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim,
it has all these things, let's say it. But also I would
I would argue that these things also pick up the theme of
שמע. Shema. Not just the מצוות, mitzvot, but the idea of מינות
minus and עבודה זרה, avoda zara, ה' אלהינו ה' אחד, Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad, you know, that's about accepting God and the true faith
and so on. And, you know, the one about the הרהור עבירה,
hirhur aveira, again, that sort of still fits within that. General theme
of doing the מצוות *Mitzvos*. So part of the פרשה *Parsha* of
שמע *Shema* is you learn תורה *Torah* and you do the מצוות
*Mitzvos*, and the basic emphasis of ציצית *Tzitzis* is you look at
the ציצית *Tzitzis* and you remember to do the right things and
to do the מצוות *Mitzvos* and not to go after your eyes.
So definitely there's an echoing of the theme and in addition getting
the מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah* of יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim *Yetzias Mitzrayim*. And
that perfectly leads us in to the last משנה *Mishnah* of the
פרק perek. *Perek*. מזכירין יציאת מצרים בלילות *Mazkirin Yetzias Mitzrayim Balaylos*, you
mention the exodus of Egypt at night, meaning that you mention, which
means in this context not like we think when we read in
the הגדה *Haggadah* that we're supposed to do, that we're supposed to
do מגיד *Maggid* פסח *Pesach* night. This is very much about the
שמע *Shema* and that you do the מצוה mitzvah. *Mitzvah* of יציאת
מצרים *Yetzias Mitzrayim*. We know the שמע *Shema* is day and night.
There's also a מצוה *Mitzvah* of remembering the Egypt, the יציאת מצרים
*Yetzias Mitzrayim*, the exodus daily, and that's why we say ציצית *Tzitzis*
as we just said. Do we say ציצית *Tzitzis* at night? That's
the question. Maybe it's only to say it once a day. Is
there a מצוה *Mitzvah* to also remember יציאת מצרים *Yetzias Mitzrayim* at
night and do we say ציצית *Tzitzis*? And the משנה *Mishnah* says
we do. אמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה *Amar Rabbi Elazar Ben Azariah*,
הרי אני כבן שבעים שנה *Harei Ani Kevhen Shivim Shanah*, I am
like I was seventy years old. He was younger, but he prayed
that he would look older. You know the story. ולא זכיתי שתאמר
יציאת מצרים בלילות *Velo Zachisi Shetiamer Yetzias Mitzrayim Balaylos*, I never merited
understanding how we could prove or that we should say the exodus
at night, that that was a מצוה *Mitzvah* as well, עד שדרשה
בן זומא *Ad Shedarshah Ben Zoma*, until Ben Zoma came and explained
the פסוק pasuk? *Pasuk* we learn it out from, which is what?
שנאמר *Shene'emar*, as it says, למען תזכור את יום צאתך מארץ מצרים
כל ימי חייך *Lema'an Tizkor Es Yom Tzeischa Me'eretz Mitzrayim Kol Yemei
Chayecha*. You have to remember the exodus all of the days of
your life. כל ימי חייך הימים *Kol Yemei Chayecha Hayamim*, the days
of your life is daytime. כל ימי חייך *Kol Yemei Chayecha*, all
of the days, meaning the fullness of the day, not just daytime,
but the full day, day and night. So that is הלילות *Halaylos*.
וחכמים אומרים *Vachachamim Omrim*, ימי חייך העולם הזה *Yemei Chayecha Ha'olam Hazeh*,
no, more literal, more sense of like the number of days, not
the fullness of each day. So the days of your life is
the days of this life. כל *Kol*, all the days of your
life, doesn't mean twice a day, but it means even you'll always
be saying it, להביא לימות המשיח *Lehavi Limos Hamashiach*. Even in the
time of משיח *Mashiach* when there will be a greater salvation, nevertheless,
we will still always remember the paradigm and the original גאולה *Geulah*
redemption of יציאת מצרים *Yetzias Mitzrayim*. Let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תניא *Tanya*. אמר להם בן זומא לחכמים *Amar Lahem
Ben Zoma Lachachamim*, Ben Zoma said to the sages, וכי מזכירין יציאת
מצרים לימות המשיח *Vechi Mazkirin Yetzias Mitzrayim Lemot Hamashiach*? Would you really
think we should be doing that, or you would do that at
the time of משיח *Mashiach*? והלא כבר נאמר *Vehalo Kevar Ne'emar*, it
says, הנה ימים באים נאם השם *Hinei Yamim Ba'im Ne'um Hashem*, days
will be coming, ולא יאמר עוד חי השם אשר העלה את בני
ישראל מארץ מצרים *Velo Ye'amer Od Chai Hashem Asher He'elah Es Benei
Yisrael Me'eretz Mitzrayim*, no longer will you say by the life of
God who took the בני ישראל *Benei Yisrael* out of Egypt. כי
אם *Ki Im*, חי השם אשר העלה ואשר הביא את זרע בית
ישראל מארץ צפונה ומכל הארצות אשר הדחתים שם *Chai Hashem Asher He'elah
Ve'asher Heivi Es Zera Beis Yisrael Me'eretz Tzafonah Umikol Ha'artzos Asher Hidachtim
Sham*. You will take an oath in the name of God who
has taken us from all of the exiles and from בבל *Bavel*
and brought us back at the time of the ultimate redemption. So
that will be the focus, the ultimate redemption, no longer יציאת מצרים
*Yetzias Mitzrayim*. So we will no longer mention it. אמרו לו *Amru
Lo*, they said back to him, לא שתעקר יציאת מצרים ממקומה *Lo
Shetia'ker Yetzias Mitzrayim Mimkomah*, doesn't mean that it loses its status, אלא
שתהא שיעבוד מלכויות עיקר ויציאת מצרים טפל לו *Ela Shetihei Shibud Malchuyos
Ikar Viyetzias Mitzrayim Tafel Lo*, that the focus will be at that
point on having been freed from the subjugation of all the other
nations and having achieved the ultimate redemption. But it doesn't mean that
יציאת מצרים *Yetzias Mitzrayim* loses its status. That still will have its
status. We'll still remember it. It'll still always have been the original
act of redemption that was the sort of, if you would, the
source of all future redemptions. כיוצא בו אתה אומר *Kiyozei Bo Atah
Omer*, similarly the idea of when something comes in addition but not
to supplant the earlier thing, it says, לא יקרא שמך עוד יעקב
lo yikarei shimcha od Yaakov. כי אם ישראל יהיה שמך *Lo Yikarei
Shimcha Od Yaakov Ki Im Yisrael Yiheyeh Shemecha*. Your name will no
longer be יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* but rather it will be ישראל *Yisrael*.
So we know that he was still called יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* after
that. לא שיעקר יעקב ממקומו *Lo Sheye'aker Yaakov Mimkomo*, not that the
name יעקב *Yaakov* will be uprooted, because God called him יעקב *Yaakov*
after that. אלא ישראל עיקר ויעקב טפל לו *Ela Yisrael Ikar Viyaakov
Tafel Lo*, the basic name from now on will be ישראל *Yisrael*,
but יעקב *Yaakov* will still be one of your names. וכן הוא
אומר *Vechen Hu Omer*, אל תזכרו ראשונות וקדמוניות אל תתבוננו *Al Tizkeru
Rishonos Vekadmoniyos Al Tisbonanu*, do not remember the early ones and the
first ones, do not sort of contemplate. אל תזכרו ראשונות *Al Tizkeru
Rishonos*, זו שיעבוד מלכויות *Zu Shibud Malchuyos*. וקדמוניות אל תתבוננו *Vekadmoniyos Al
Tisbonanu*, זו יציאת מצרים *Zu Yetzias Mitzrayim*. So this is both the,
you won't remember, meaning you won't remember the servitude of the early
ones and of the קדמוניות *Kadmoniyos*. So both the שיעבוד מלכויות *Shibud
Malchuyos*, I don't know why it's called ראשונות *Rishonos*, but anyway, and
of you'll remember the exile as it were, both of the early
ones of the מלכויות *Malchuyos* and also of יציאת מצרים *Yetzias Mitzrayim*,
so you will always remember both. Okay. הנני עושה חדשה עתה תצמח
*Hineni Oseh Chadashah Atah Titzmach*, I will now do a new thing,
now the salvation will rise up. And therefore, you know, you will
no longer be mired in the שיעבוד *Shibud* of the previous ones.
תני דבי יוסף זו מלחמת גוג ומגוג. Gog u'Magog. This is the
war of גוג ומגוג. משל למה הדבר דומה לאדם שהיה מהלך בדרך
ופגע בו זאב. Mashal l'ma hadavar domeh l'adam shehayah mehalech baderech u'paga
bo ze'ev. A person was going on the way and he encountered
a wolf. וניצל ממנו, v'nitzal mimenu, he was saved from it. והיה
מספר והולך מעשה זאב, v'hayah mesaper v'holech ma'aseh ze'ev, he would tell
everybody who would listen about this amazing miracle that he was saved
from the wolf. ופגע בו ארי, u'paga bo ari, then the next
time he encountered a lion. וניצל ממנו, v'nitzal mimenu, he was saved
from it. והיה מספר והולך מעשה ארי, v'hayah mesaper v'holech ma'aseh ari,
then he told everybody about the lion. Oh my God, this was
so amazing, I was saved from a lion. פגע בו נחש וניצל
ממנו, paga bo nachash v'nitzal mimenu, then he encountered a snake, which
presumably is more dangerous than a lion, וניצל ממנו. v'nitzal mimenu. שכח
מעשה שניהם, shachach ma'aseh sheneihem, he forgot about both of them. והיה
מספר והולך מעשה נחש, v'hayah mesaper v'holech ma'aseh nachash, and he would
go ahead and he would talk about the snake and not about
the earlier ones. So אף כך ישראל צרות אחרונות משכחות את הראשונות.
af kach Yisrael tzaros achronos meshakechos es harishonos. Similarly for the Jewish
people, the later ones make us, ברוך השם Baruch Hashem or whatever,
have sort of like the גמרא Gemara before about דאילת צרה בשעתה,
d'ayelas tzara b'sha'atah, we have one series of afflictions after the next.
So when we have the new one, it seems even bigger than
the last one and we forgot the last one and we just
focus on the new. Now I have to tell you that the
פשט pshat
here, this משל mashal is saying that it's משכחות, meshakechos, the other.
I know, I know. So I agree. So it's a little funny
way to end because if anything this seems to more support the
opinion that says that we won't be saying יציאת מצרים in the
future because we'll have forgotten it
because of the extent of
our current suffering and affliction is that much greater and that
overwhelms. So I really don't have an answer except if the גמרא's
Gemara point is that's why we have to continue to remember, because
since human nature is to focus on only the most recent, and
therefore דוקא davka the מצוה is to not forget even the earlier
ones because the earlier ones were also miracles and we can't just
even though the inclination is that the last one is the greatest
miracle perhaps and the one we'll certainly subjectively remember the most, but
maybe דוקא davka that's why we're told that we have to continue
to remember the earlier ones. But you're right, it's a little funny.
The גמרא Gemara doesn't exactly sort of close the circle. Let's finish
till the end of the פרק. Okay, since we're talking about supplanting
versus not supplanting, let's take a look. אברם הוא אברהם. Avram hu
Avraham. So this is from דברי הימים. Divrei HaYamim. It says אברם
Avram is אברהם. Avraham. בתחילה נעשה אב לארם, B'tchila na'aseh av l'Aram,
first he was אברם, Avram, like אב av just for ארם, Aram,
the people of his nation, which was ארם נהריים. Aram Naharayim. ולבסוף
נעשה אב לכל העולם כולו. u'l'vasof na'aseh av l'chol ha'olam kulo. The
ה He meant אב av for the entire world. אב המון גוים.
Av hamon goyim. So somehow the אברהם, Avraham, המון, hamon, the father
of many nations.
שרי היא שרה. Sarai hi Sarah. Also from דברי הימים. Divrei HaYamim.
שרי Sarai is שרה. Sarah. בתחילה נעשית שרי לאומתה, B'tchila na'asis Sarai
l'umasa, ולבסוף נעשית שרה לכל העולם כולו. u'l'vasof na'asis Sarah l'chol ha'olam
kulo. So originally she was שרי Sarai like individual, 'my master', so
for her nation, and in the end she would be שרה Sarah
without any possessive, 'the master' for all people. תני בר קפרא. Tanni
Bar Kappara. כל הקורא לאברהם אברם עובר בעשה. Kol hakoreh l'Avraham Avram
over b'aseh. So where יעקב the name did not supplant, by אברהם
Avraham the name did supplant. And anybody who calls אברהם Avraham אברם
Avram actually transgresses a positive מצוה. שנאמר והיה שמך אברהם, shene'emar v'hayah
shimcha Avraham, your name shall be Abraham. רבי אליעזר אומר עובר בלאו.
Rabbi Eliezer omer over b'lav. Not only that, if you do it
you're transgressing a negative prohibition. שנאמר ולא יקרא עוד את שמך אברם.
shene'emar v'lo yikarei od es shimcha Avram. You shall no longer, not
just meaning a declaration of fact, people won't call it, but it's
actually a prohibition. People shall not call you anymore אברם. Avram. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה הקורא לשרה שרי הכי נמי. Ela
me'ata hakoreh l'Sarah Sarai hachi nami. So maybe the same should be
true about שרה Sarah and שרי. Sarai. So maybe we should say
it. So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם קודשא בריך הוא אמר
לאברהם. Hasam Kudsha Brich Hu amar l'Avraham. שרי אשתך לא תקרא את
שמה שרי כי שרה שמה. Sarai ishtecha lo tikra es shemah Sarai
ki Sarah shemah. That God
said to אברהם, Avraham, שרי Sarai your wife,
her name shall not be called שרי, Sarai, rather
שרה. Sarah. So right.
You should not call her, not anyone else.
Right, I know, לא תקרא, lo tikra, but it's not even, right,
thank you, right, that's it. It's in the second person. It's
not לא יקרא lo yikarei about other, shall not be called, which
is to everybody, but לא תקרא, lo tikra, אתה לא תקרא, ata
lo tikra, you shall not call her name, but it's not to
everybody. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה הקורא ליעקב יעקב הכי
נמי. Ela me'ata hakoreh l'Yaakov Yaakov hachi nami. So maybe by יעקב
also, says right, it says what's the פסוק?
לא יקרא שמך עוד יעקב. So what?
So the גמרא says שאני התם, shani hasam, no, there it's different.
דהדר אהדריה קרא, d'hadar ahadreih kra, דכתיב ויאמר אלהים לישראל. d'chtiv vayomer
Elohim l'Yisrael. The primary. But
by אברם *Avram* we say that it's actually fully prohibited and by
שרה *Sarah* only not because God was talking only to אברם *Avram*
and not generally. And then the גמרא *Gemara* says מתיב רב יוסף
בר אבין ואי תימא רב יוסף בר זידא אתה הוא ה׳ אלקים
אשר בחרת באברם *mativ Rav Yosef bar Abin v'itayma Rav Yosef bar
Zida Atah hu Hashem Elokim asher bacharta be'Avram*
you God chose אברם *Avram*. So there the פסוק *pasuk* did not
say אברהם *Avraham*. So אמרי התם נביא הוא דקא מסדר לשבחיה דרחמנא
מאי דהוה מעיקרא *amrei hatam navi hu d'ka mesader lishvachei d'Rachmana mai
d'hava meikara*. There the נביא *navi* is praising about the past: you
had chosen him when he was אברם *Avram* and you gave him
the name אברהם *Avraham*. So, so but you're not actually now referring
to him as אברם *Avram*. Now the question becomes and somebody actually
asked me this question and I've also wondered this, so let's say
you're giving a you're talking about, you're giving a שיעור *shiur* on
פרשת לך לך *parshas Lech Lecha* and can you say when God
says to אברם *Avram* לך לך מארצך *Lech Lecha me'artzecha* right? Or
do you have to say when God said to אברהם *Avraham*? Now
most of us anyway would say when God said to אברהם *Avraham*.
But would you be עובר *over* on this? Would this be like
the last line of the גמרא *Gemara* that you're just talking about
at that time that was his name? Or not, since you're saying
when God—there it's in the context: You chose him as—he was אברם
*Avram* and you chose him and gave him the name אברהם *Avraham*.
But when you're actually talking about what he did, you have to
use his new name, you can't be using his old name even
if you're talking about what he did when he had the old
name. Or not? So I don't know, it's a little ambiguous. I'm
מחמיר *machmir* about it, not like I have too much of a
יצר הרע *yetzer hara*. Normally we would anyway just call him אברהם
*Avraham*. But, but you know anyway it is interesting in terms of
what exactly are those parameters. Obviously to say you're really עובר *over*
לאו *lav*, really עובר *over* עשה *asei*, most assume that's a little
bit of an אסמכתא *asmachta*, we would not say it's a real
biblical thing. But nevertheless the גמרא *Gemara* treats it seriously, so it
does raise those interesting questions. Okay, so we'll end with this for
now. Nice ending of that, both, mix of both הלכה *halacha* and
אגדתא *aggadata* around the ברכות *brachot* around שמע *Shma* and we will
pick up with the beginning of the second פרק *perek* tomorrow morning.
Okay, כל טוב *kol tuv* everybody, לילה טוב *Laila Tov*.